Guide to the Silver Bow County Sanitary Conditions report photographs 1908-1912
Montana Historical Society
Silver Bow County Sanitary Conditions report photographs
1908-1912
Montana Historical Society Photograph Archives
Lot 008
Silver Bow County (Mont.). Health Department
1 box 134 photographic prints
This collection contains photographs taken to illustrate a "Report of Investigation of Sanitary Conditions in Mines and of the Conditions Under Which the Miners Live in Silver Bow County", 1908-1912. The images show sanitary conditions in Butte neighborhoods, local dairies, the county hospital, and underground mines. Each photograph has the description which accompanied it in the report.
The photographs in this collection accompanied a report entitled "Report of Investigation of Sanitary Conditions in Mines, and of the Conditions Under Which the Miners Live in Silver Bow County." This report presented the findings of a study of sanitary conditions in below ground and surface workings of the Butte mines, residences in Butte and Silver Bow County, local dairies, and the county hospital or poor farm. This investigation was probably undertaken by county health officials and was an attempt to determine the causes of wide spread incidence of tuberculosis in Silver Bow County. The data was collected during the years 1908-1912.
These photographs show sanitary conditions found by the inspectors in the Butte mines, in a few of the dairies adjacent to Butte, around dwellings and boarding houses, and conditions found at the county poor farm from 1908 to 1912. The photographs include views of the Anaconda, Gagnon, Little Minah, Never Sweat, Original, St. Lawrence, and Stewart mines, as well as mines that are not identified. The dairies photographed were the Crescent, Imperial, North Star, Reliable, Springtown, and Summit Valley. Photographs of residences often include street addresses and show exterior views of yards and streets. The photographs were taken in Butte, Centerville, Meaderville, and Walkerville.
The photographs in this collection are unattributed.
The photographs were arranged by subject and organized into four subject-based series: Series I. Dairies, Series II. Hospitals, Series III. Houses, and Series IV. Mines
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
See the "Report of Investigation of Sanitary Conditions in Mines and of the Conditions Under Which the Miners Live in Silver Bow County", SC 89, for related manuscript materials.
This collection is indexed under the following headings. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Sanitation -- Montana -- Butte
Butte (Mont.); Montana
Photographic prints
Miners
City and Town Life; Labor History; Mines and Mineral Resources; Montana; Photographs
- Dairies, Series I
  - Crescent, Summit Valley, Springtown, North Star, Reliable, Imperial and East Side dairies (includes views of barns, milk houses, milk cans, cattle, dog and stable in Butte), 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
- Hospitals, Series II
  - Silver Bow County Hospital (interior views with hospital equipment and beds, men sitting and lying in beds), 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- Houses, Series III
  - Butte, Montana: exterior views of residences and yards at East Mercury, East Park, East Transit, and South Dakota Streets (includes refuse in back yard of the Florence Hotel, chickens, piles of manure, privies, and washing on line), 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Butte, Montana: exterior views of residences and back yards at East Park, East Broadway, Lee Avenue, East Mercury North Wyoming, West Center, East LaPlatte, North Montana, and Second Avenue (includes toliets, children at play, sewers, women, refuse, manure piles, washing on line, goats, turkey, stove, alleys, and chickens), 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Centerville area of Butte, Montana: exterior views of residences with back yards at O'Neill, Bennett, Laplatte and Minah Streets (includes children with dogs, manure, goats, refuse, laundry, geese, and a cow) and Big Butte., 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Meaderville, Montana: rear of Main Street (includes man with foot on a barrel, refuse in street), 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Walkerville, Montana: exterior views of residences and yards at Transit and West Daly Streets with manure piles and privies, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- Mines, Series IV
  - Miners at Stewart and Gagnon Mines, ventilator shaft, showers, washroom, lockers, "dry", explosives, toilet cars in Original Mine and hoist, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Miners, toilet car, drill, ventilation tubes and shafts, mine railroad car, lantern, water tank, and fungus on timbers, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - The "Dry" at Stewart Mine, lockers, washroom, toilet, miners, Little Minah Mine, horses and stables underground, jacks, drills, mine railroad car, powder magazine, ventilation pipes, and hoists, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Miners, toilet, mine railroad cars, shift bosses eating, jack in Mountain Consolidated Mine, mouth of shaft with hoist, water pump, horse and barn, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Miners at mouth of shaft at Never Sweat Mine, horses and stables in St. Lawrence Mine, mouth of shaft and goat at Anaconda Mine, electric fan, fire doors, John P. O'Neill, hoisting engine, 1908-1912 (Box-folder 1 / 12)